Southern Tenant Farmers Union Records on Microfilm 5204 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- November 1944 to December 1944, Undated 1944, and January 1945 to February 1945. (Reel 28)
  - January, 1945, 4 (Reel 28)
    As the year began, Mitchell wrote Leon Schachter that the STFU had no prospects for finding jobs for its members except in New Jersey (3). Despite his pessimism, Mitchell wrote the WMC about supplying workers for war plants in Louisville, Ky. (3); the Commission did not take up his offer, for reasons outlined in a WMC internal memorandum which appears in the papers (12). Two hopeful signs did begin to lift the gloom: Marvin W. Hook of the Meat Cutters Union wrote about sending men for packing house jobs in Cleveland, Ohio (10), and the Frank M. Wilson Co. of Stockton, Calif. wrote about employing 100 to 200 workers over the summer (19). Heifers for Relief, an organization founded by the Church of the Brethren, wrote about distributing cows to needy Arkansas families (25, 28). Finally, the union filed suit against W. E. Fallas, an Arkansas planter accused of charging usurious interest rates to his tenants; the court brief and a press release are in the papers (20)
  - February, 1945, 5 (Reel 28)
    Mitchell and Schachter both became convinced that the prime obstacle facing their "organized migration" program was the opposition of local WMC officials in Memphis, New Jersey, and other places. There is a great deal of correspondence during February on this problem, especially between Mitchell and Schachter, between Mitchell and Paul Sifton of the National Farmers' Union (8, 13); and between the STFU and the WMC. STFU Vice-Presidents F.R. Betton and J.E. Clayton wrote to the Heifers for Relief Committee, setting forth a plan to distribute the promised cows through the Arkansas Farmers Co-operative (8). Rev. David Burgess submitted a lengthy report on his work during the month, including an account of a two-day Ministers' Institute held a Cotton Plant, Ark. (28).
- March 1945 to May 1945. (Reel 29)
  - March, 1945, 1 (Reel 29)
    As David Burgess reported to Mitchell early in the month, the Farm Security Administration had decided to sell at auction the Delmo Labor Homes Project in Southeast Missouri which had been built five years earlier to house evicted tenant families (8). An intensive campaign got underway immediately to save the Delmo homes, a campaign which might best be followed in the correspondence and reports of David Burgess. On this subject, see also Mitchell to Alfred Baker Lewis (19), the Minutes of the Tenants' Committee at Delmo (20), and a report on a delegation of Delmo tenants which went to Washington to meet with FSA officials (31). Readers wishing to keep track of the shipments of STFU workers might consult the "Schedule of Seasonal Work Orders", which includes information on the dates of employment, pay promised, and number of workers to be sent (20). Finally, the union once again began to recruit black college students for summer jobs at the Deerfield Packing Co. in Bridgeton, NJ; a memorandum on the agreement with Deerfield appears on March 24
  - April, 1945, 2 (Reel 29)
    Efforts to save the Delmo Labor Homes were focused on Congress, as the STFU lobbied for legislation which would direct the FSA to sell the homes to the residents at a reasonable price. The members of Congress most directly involved in the campaign were Senators Frank P. Briggs of Missouri and William Langer of North Dakota, as well as Congressmen Orville Zimmerman of Missouri and Frank Hook of Michigan. The key documents include: a "Fact Sheet" on Delmo by David Burgess (3); the FSA to Zimmerman, stating their policy on sales of projects (10); an exchange between Mitchell and the FSA on complaints of Delmo tenants 912,17); and a detailed memorandum for Burgess to Mitchell on his conversation with FSA Regional Director Stephen C. Hughes in Indianapolis (n.d.). There are lengthy reports from organizer Ruby Warren at the Edgar F. Hurff Co. in New Jersey (9,18,21,23), and a memorandum by W.R. Ogg of the Farm Bureau replying to the STFU claim that the South had a surplus of farm labor (9)
  - May, 1945, 3 (Reel 29)
    Much of the day-to-day correspondence during May concerns the recruitment of 300 black college students for summer jobs at the Deerfield Packing Co. in New Jersey; see especially a press release on the project (30) and a "Report on Student Workers", which provides a breakdown on the number of students sent by individual colleges (n.d.). Hopes for saving the Delmo Homes were centered on an "Independent Tenants' Committee" of prominent St. Louis citizens which planned to buy the homes and resell them to the tenants over an extended period of time; information on this committee can be found in a flood of correspondence on Delmo which appears during the last three days of the month and in a letter from FSA Administrator Frank Hancock to Rev. L.S. Thornton of St. Louis (18). STFU Vice-President J.E. Clayton represented the union at the United Nations Peace Conference in San Francisco and sent home reports on his work (1,3,5,12,27,28).
- June 1945 to September 1945. (Reel 30)
  - June, 1945, 1 (Reel 30)
    On the continuing campaign to save the Delmo Homes, see two detailed letters by Rev. L.S. "Ted" Thornton on the work of the St. Louis Committee (5,16) and a nine-page memorandum by David Burgess entitled "Basic Facts About the Delmo Labor Homes Project, and Their Relationship to the Future of the FSA" (25). There is also a memorandum by Burgess on ways to strengthen the STFU (20). For information on the college girls at the Deerfield Packing Co., see the letters of Mae Pearl Kelley (5, 8)
  - July, 1945, 2 (Reel 30)
    On July 10, the STFU sent 90 workers to the Frank M. Wilson Co. in Stockton, Calif.; for information on this subject, see the lengthy exchange between Mitchell and the company on the problems which arose (24, 27) and reports from Carrie Dilworth (13), Moses Brown (22), and Roy Clay (24), all at Stockton. For summaries of the STFU's current activities, see Mitchell's memoranda to the NSF (7) and to the STFU Executive Council (13). David Burgess and Cong. Frank Hook both testified before the House Agriculture Committee on behalf of the Delmo tenants; their statements appear (10) as well as a long letter from Burgess to Mitchell on the same topic (31). Of special interest is a draft of a report by Dr. Arthur F. Raper of the Bureau of Agricultural Economics on the effect of increasing mechanization on cotton production in the South 914). Finally, there is a memorandum by Mitchell on the situation at the Campbell Soup Co. where the Food, Tobacco, and Agricultural Workers Union, CIO (formerly UCAPAWA) threatened to strike if STFU seasonal workers were employed (26)
  - August, 1945, 3 (Reel 30)
    Reports on the situation at the Delmo homes arrived from organizer Bill Johnson and David Burgess; see also Burgess' monthly report (31). Mae Pearl Kelley kept Mitchell informed on what was happening at the Deerfield Packing Co. (3,10,20,27). During the last week of the month, a furious fight erupted when the STFU learned of Department of Agriculture plans to enact a wage ceiling for cotton picking in the South by holding state-wide referendums. The Department's Arkansas Wage Board held hearings on the wage ceiling at Osceola and Forrest City; the papers include minutes of the hearings compiled by Lewis Henderson, a friend of the union from Little Rock (29,30) and a scathing report on the Osceola session by David Burgess entitled "A Preview of American Fascism" (29)
  - September, 1945, 4 (Reel 30)
    The most important topic for this month is the union's unsuccessful attempt to halt the wage ceiling imposed on cotton picking. Items related to the wage ceiling fight include: minutes of a meeting of the Delta Council Labor Committee held July 12 during which the Council voted to ask the government for a wage ceiling (6); Mitchell's statement to the Secretary of Agriculture entitled "A Ceiling on Cotton Pickers' Wages" (10) and his report to the Executive Council on his trip to Washington (18); Mitchell to Cong. Frank Hook, explaining the effect of the ceiling on cotton production (21); and a long memorandum from union lawyer K.T. Sutton on the prospects for obtaining an injunction against the Arkansas USDA Wage Board (n.d.). On the continuing fight to save the Delmo Homes, see the exchange of correspondence between Mitchell and David Burgess (11,24,27).
- October 1945 to December 1945, Undated 1945, and Miscellaneous Union Business 1945. (Reel 31)
  - October, 1945, 1 (Reel 31)
    On October 10, STFU filed a petition for injunction in Federal District Court to restrain the Arkansas USDA Wage Board from setting a wage ceiling of $2.05 per hundred for cotton picking; a copy of the petition and anSTFU press release about it appear at that date. Further information on the wage ceiling fight can be found in the correspondence K.T. Sutton and in a letter from F.R. Betton, who claimed that white tenants at Cotton Plant were so infuriated at the ceiling that they planned to form anSTFU local (31). Letters and reports concerning the campaign to purchase the Delmo Labor Homes from the FSA appear throughout the month, but become especially heavy during the last few days. The union held a series of pre-convention meetings in both Arkansas and Missouri during October; the papers include the minutes of one such meeting held at Dumas, Ark. (13). Finally, reports of trouble arrived from the Frank M. Wilson Co. in Stockton, Calif., where some STFU members had joined FTAW-CIO; see the exchange between Moses Brown and Mitchell on this subject (1,11)
  - November, 1945, 2 (Reel 31)
    After several months of struggle, David Burgess finally concluded arrangements for the purchase of the Delmo Homes through Sherwood Eddy's Co-operative Foundation in New York; the papers include the draft and final copy of Eddy's bid to the FSA (1,3). The STFU petition for injunction in the wage ceiling dispute was dismissed in Federal Court; on this matter see K.T. Sutton to Mitchell, explaining the court's action (10), as well as a WDL memorandum to Sutton, pointing out defects in the petition (2). Two other items are of special interest: Mitchell to Clayton, setting forth his general policy on buying land for the purpose of colonizing STFU members (15); and Mitchell to Lewis Henderson on the current strength and activities of the STFU in Arkansas (26)
  - December, 1945, 3 (Reel 31)
    The Twelfth Annual STFU Convention was held at St. Louis, Mo. on December 11 to 13; the papers include the program, a typed copy of the Proceedings, a handwritten list of delegates and visitors, the report of the Executive Council, and a two-page telegram from Gardner Jackson to the convention (11). There is also a lengthy letter from Jackson to Mitchell on the wage ceiling problem (18), as well as one from Mitchell to the NAACP on the same subject (7). There is a detailed letter from Mitchell to Alfred Baker Lewis, Secretary of NSF, on the problems which the STFU had experienced with the Delmo Housing Committee in St. Louis (20)
  - No Date, 1945, 4 (Reel 31)
    Memorandum from Mitchell to David Burgess on "Early Organization in Southeast Missouri"; Agreements between the STFU and the Edgar F. Hurff Co., the P.J. Ritter Co., the Basic Vegetable Co., and the California Conserving Co.; an STFU press release on the Delmo Labor Homes campaign; letters from Mississippi organizer B.J. Bennett; a two-page questionnaire completed by Charlie Smith on his settlement with his landlord; approximately 25 pages of handwritten notes by David Burgess, dealing primarily with the Delmo Homes; and a Model Landlord and Tenant Contract drawn up by K.T. Sutton
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1945, 5 (Reel 31)
    Folders 1096 to 1098 -- Correspondence from college students concerning summer jobs. Folder 1110 -- Not Filmed. Folders 1111 to 1115 -- Monthly reports from locals, 1945. Folder 1116 -- Bonds submitted by local secretaries -- one sample filmed. Folder 1117 -- Charter applications, 1945. Folder 1119 -- Lists of local STFU officers and officer election forms, 1945. Folder 1121 -- Not Filmed. Folder 1123 -- Landlord-tenant contracts. Folder 1124 -- Auditor's Report, Nov. 1, 1944 to Oct. 31, 1945. Also, monthly financial statements, June to November, 1945.
- January 1946 to July 1948, includes Undated and Miscellaneous Union Business 1946-1947. (Reel 32)
  - 1946, 1 (Reel 32)
    The papers become very spotty during both 1946 and 1947, with an average of about ten items appearing each month. During the first few months of 1946, the major topic is the attempt to roll back the USDA wage ceiling for cotton workers. During the summer, the STFU, which had changed its name to the National Farm Labor Union (NFLU) became affiliated with the AF of L; the formal NFLU request for affiliation is dated August 14. Also during the summer, the union became embroiled in a furious fight with the FTA-CIO over the seasonal employment of NFLU members at the Campbell Soup Co. in Camden, NJ. The CIO union threatened to strike the plant if NFLU workers were hired, and the NFLU retaliated with charges that the FTA-CIO was Communist-led. The National Farmers Union also became involved in the conflict, which ended when the company gave in to the CIO demands. On this subject, see the affidavit of George Stith, the NFLU representative at Campbell (Sept. 14). At the end of the year, the union started a campaign to stop the illegal entry of Mexican Nationals into Texas, where they were used to depress the wage standards of American farm labor; see especially the detailed letter from a U.S. Customs Patrol inspector at Alpine, Texas to Mitchell on why his service was unable to stop the "wetback" immigration (Dec. 9)
  - No Date, 1946, 2 (Reel 32)
    "Draft for a Union Farm Agreement"; press releases on the appointment of Barney B. Taylor as NFLU Organization Director, on affiliation with the AF of L, on the trouble at the Campbell Soup Co., and on the defeat of the USDA wage ceiling program; Voice of America address by the USDA wage ceiling program; Voice of America address by H.L. Mitchell on the NFLU program; Constitution of the NFLU
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1946, 3 (Reel 32)
    Folder 1128 -- Lists of workers sent to food processing plants in New Jersey and Maryland, 1946
  - January to July, 1947, 4 (Reel 32)
    The Thirteenth Annual Convention was held at Washington, D.C. from January 13 to 15; the papers include a press release, the report of the Executive Council, and the NFLU Constitution as amended by the Convention (Jan. 13). Other items of special interest include: two formal statements by Mitchell, one to the House Agriculture Committee on Farm Labor Bill H.R. 3367 (June 18), and the other to a USDA hearing on "Minimum Wage Rates of Sugar Cane Workers" (July 26); an exchange between Mitchell and the U.S. Commissioner of Immigration and Naturalization on the "wetback" problem (April 17 and 23); and a memorandum by NFLU Texas organizer George Webber on the importation of Mexican Nationals in the Rio Grande Valley (July 15), followed by a reply from the U.S. Immigration and Naturalization Service (July 31)
  - August to December, 1947, 5 (Reel 32)
    On September 2, there is a memorandum to the Robert Marshall Civil Liberties Trust Fund proposing a survey of the civil liberties of migratory farm workers to be conducted by Ernesto Galarza. Virtually all the correspondence from October through December concerns the strike of 1,200 workers at the Di Giorgio Ranch in Bakersfield, Calif., called by the NFLU with the aid of the California Federation of Labor. There are frequent mimeographed strike bulletins, as well as a list of donors to the strike relief fund (Dec. 18), and an anti-union booklet prepared by the Special Citizens Committee Investigating Di Giorgio Farms (Dec. 17). Finally, the Fourteenth Annual Convention was held at Little Rock, Ark. on December 12 to 14; the papers include a magazine article by Mitchell on the convention, the report of the Executive Council, the program, the resolutions passed, and the NFLU Constitution (Dec. 12)
  - No Date, 1947, 6 (Reel 32)
    Address by H.L. Mitchell to the Second Annual Convention of Midwest Sugar Workers; several press releases on the Di Giorgio strike; NFLU memorandum on plans for organization in Texas, New Mexico, Arizona, and California; address by Mitchell to the California State Federation of Labor; a six-page statement on the NFLU program; memorandum by Mitchell on the background and activities of FTA-CIO President Donald Henderson
  - Miscellaneous Union Business, 1947, 7 (Reel 32)
    Folder 1133 -- Lists of workers sent to food processing plants in New Jersey, 1947
  - January to March, 1948, 8 (Reel 32)
    The Di Giorgio strike continues to be the topic of greatest importance in the papers through the end of March. The reader may best follow the sequence of strike events through the numerous strike bulletins, issued approximately every ten days, and through the correspondence of NFLU California organizer Jim Wrightson. During the last week of January and the first week of February, several sizable contributions to the strike relief fund arrived from AF of L unions; a complete list of donors appears on February 6. Also related is a statement by Mitchell presented before the Senate Fact Finding Committee on Subversive Activities in California (Feb. 18)
  - April, 1948, 9 (Reel 32)
    Black workers at the Edgar F. Hurff Co. in New Jersey loyal to FTA-CIO staged a wildcat strike during April demanding that the company sever its agreement with the AFL Meat Cutters Union. Since the NFLU placed its own workers at the Hurff Co. through the Meat Cutters, the union became directly involved in the dispute. See the detailed reports of F.R. Betton, who was sent to New Jersey to help quash the strike. The NFLU's own strike at the Di Giorgio Corp. continued and may be followed through the strike bulletins (3, 18). There is some correspondence with the Hollywood AFL Film Council about a film produced by the Council on the Di Giorgio strike (15, 22). In April and continuing until October, there is a sizable volume of correspondence to and from I. Lee Parker, NFLU Labor Placement Director, about seasonal jobs outside the South. Finally, in the undated section at the end of the month, there is a lengthy "Organizational Repot on California Farm Labor" by Hank Hasiwar
  - May, 1948, 10 (Reel 32)
    The Di Giorgio strike again becomes the most important topic in the correspondence in May, especially after the shooting of strike leader Jim Price on May 18. In addition to the flood of telegrams and press releases following the shooting, see the length report by Ernesto Galarza entitled "Poverty in the Valley of Plenty" (1), Mitchell to organizer Hank Hasiwar on a plan to picket Di Giorgio plants throughout the country (6), and the opinion of Herbert S. Thatcher, AFL General Counsel, on the legal ramifications of the picketing scheme (11). There is some correspondence about placing black college students in summer jobs, although not as much as in 1944 and 1945
  - June, 1948, 11 (Reel 32)
    The employees at the Hurff Co. voted in an NLRB election to replace the AFL Meat Cutters Union with the FTA-CIO as their bargaining agent; see the reports of WC Banks, the NFLU representative at Hurff (8,17). The Di Giorgio Corp. obtained an injunction against the NFLU's nationwide picketing scheme, terming it a "secondary boycott"; information on the injunction may be found in two long letters from Ernesto Galarza (23, 27) and in an NFLU press release (28). The union issued a statement on the importation of foreign nationals to depress American farm wages (4), and Mitchell complained to USES Director Robert C. Goodwin on the use of West Indian workers in the Florida sugar cane industry (15). There is a report on the status of the college student recruitment drive (8) and two letters from NSF Secretary Hazel Whitmen on the work of her organization (9,26)
  - July, 1948, 12 (Reel 32)
    For detailed information on the situation in California, the reader should consult the multi-paged, single-spaced letters of Ernesto Galarza, who seems to have gone everywhere and met everyone in the state (5,18,26). Beginning on July 12 and continuing for several months, contributions to the Di Giorgio strike fund poured in from AFL-affiliated unions throughout the country. A good summary of the NFLU seasonal employment program in New Jersey and Pennsylvania appears in a bulletin Mitchell sent to his Southern locals on July 23.
- August 1948 to December 1948, Undated 1948, and Miscellaneous Union Business 1948. (Reel 33)
  - August, 1948, 1 (Reel 33)
    The progress of the seasonal labor program may be followed in the letters from I. Lee Parker to Mitchell (3,7,11,18) and in the correspondence from the J.H. Heinz Co., which employed 80 NFLU workers at its plants in Muscatine, Iowa and Bowling Green, Ohio. The NFLU statement to the NLRB on the Di Giorgio injunction suit appears on August 3; see also the report from Hank Hasiwar on the court proceedings (18). A USIS Border Patrol guard at El Paso, Texas wrote Mitchell about the numerous violations of the immigration law at his station (1). There is a three-page mimeographed letter sent out by the Southeast Louisiana Dairy Farmers Union to its members explaining its decision to switch affiliation from the Teamsters Union to the NFLU (5), and a letter from Mitchell to AFL President William Green, asking for assistance in hiring two new organizers to work with the Louisiana dairy farmers and with citrus laborers in Florida (16)
  - September, 1948, 2 (Reel 33)
    The papers include a statement to Mitchell on the proposed importation of 5,000 Mexican Nationals into California for farm work (9) and a letter from Galarza to the U.S. Department of State on the same subject (20). There are several reports from I. Lee Parker on his new job organizing Louisiana dairy farmers. On the Di Giorgio strike, see Mitchell to Hank Hasiwar, advising him on strategy (1)
  - October, 1948, 3 (Reel 33)
    From October 16 to 18, the NFLU held a conference at Laredo, Texas with the Confederacion Proletaria Nacional of Mexico in an effort to stop the illegal flow of Mexican farm workers into the United States; there is a summary report by Galarza on the conference (18). While the conference was in session, a flood of Mexicans crossed the border at El Paso, Texas and were taken into custody by the border patrol, which promptly turned them over to the USES for employment in Texas. On the El Paso incident, see Mitchell's telegram to President Truman (17), William Green's protests to Attorney General Tom Clark (21), and two lengthy reports from Galarza (24, 28)
  - November, 1948, 4 (Reel 33)
    the Fifteenth Annual Convention was held at Cincinnati, Ohio on November 12 to 14; the papers include the program, the report of the Executive Board, a report on the convention by NSF Executive Secretary Hazel Whitman, and several press releases (12 to 14). There is a report by Galarza entitled "Civil Liberties and Spanish-speaking people of the southwest states" (1). Finally, there is a set of minutes of a Board of Directors meeting of the National Sharecroppers Fund called to discuss the NSF's poor performance in recent months; the minutes include an analysis of the NSF cash flow over the previous year (30)
  - December, 1948, 5 (Reel 33)